I don't want to get into a whole
internet fight here, but
>> This is David Malan. He's a Harvard
professor famous for transforming CS50
into a world-class online computer
science course.
>> How do you keep people engaged for a
3-hour lecture?
>> I think a lot of it honestly comes from
a place of insecurity. Like I really
don't want to be the one on stage in
front of a board audience.
>> I'm curious what you would say to
someone that has that mindset that you
don't need to actually know how the
computer works.
>> If you're going to call yourself an
engineer, you should be understanding
everything that's happening among those
layers.
>> We also discuss how AI is impacting
cheating and enrollment.
>> It's harder for us now to hand to the
administrative board of Harvard or the
honor council, so to speak, a smoking
gun.
>> Maybe programming will be useless in the
future.
Here's the full episode.
>> You posted this photo of your first
assignment in CS50, not as the teacher,
but as the student actually, under Brian
Kernighan. What was your experience like
getting into computer science?
>> Yeah, it's a really good question. So, I
was that problem set, my first Hello
World World program was in September of
when I first stepped foot in a class
called CS50. I was a sophomore at the
time, um and hadn't honestly gotten up
the nerve until sophomore year to even
consider taking the class. So, like when
I came into college first year, and this
is a story I tell at the very start of
CS50 most years, I really gravitated
toward fields that were more familiar,
more comfortable for me, and I share
with students that I really liked
constitutional law. Like that was my
favorite class in high school, and I
figured that meant when you get to
college, I should probably major or
concentrate, as we say at Harvard, in
government. And so, for the first year,
year and a half, I was heads down
focused on studying government, but when
I finally got up the nerve to like
follow some friends, I think, into the
CS50 classroom that day when this very
well-reputed computer scientist, Brian
Kernighan, was at the helm uh for just
that one year. I was totally hooked and
it was the first time in like 19 years
that homework was fun. So much so that
when the week's problem sets or
assignments would come out, I would look
forward to going back to my dorm on
Friday evenings to work through the
night on my CS 50 problem sets. So, I
felt like that was a sign that I'm
supposed to study computer science.
>> And I I saw on that assignment it says
minus two and there's a little there's a
little note there that I I actually
couldn't quite make out. Do you looking
back now as the teacher, like why did
you get a minus two there?
>> It was something stupid and very easily
redressable, but I did not start off
computer science or CS 50 on the best
foot. I got two minus two out of
probably two points on Hello World.
>> What was the the story behind you going
from a student to the teacher
eventually?
>> I had an opportunity my senior year of
college to teach a introductory course
in computer science at Harvard's
Extension School, which is the
continuing ed program largely for
adults. The course was literally called
Introduction to Computers and the
Internet cuz in 1999 we were still in
the habit of introducing people to
computers and the Internet as opposed to
taking it for granted more so nowadays.
Um and it was me in a room full of 100
or so adults. I was easily the youngest
person in the room at like 21 years old.
The story I usually share is that that
was the first and last time I wore
suspenders cuz I was so determined to
project being older um even though I was
still just a senior. Um but that really
wet my appetite in turn not only for
more computer science even though that
was very introductory and more
technology focused for teaching. Um and
over time I real over the next few years
I realized that doors would be closed to
me if I wanted to teach at a place like
Harvard College and I eventually
returned to Harvard to do my PhD for 5
years in computer science. And then in
2007 when I was finishing up the former
professor, my own advisor, uh was moving
on to be Dean of the school and so there
was this vacancy at the helm of CS50 and
I somehow talked my way into the job. Um
they were interested in having a senior
uh
faculty member take over the course. I
guess they weren't able to find someone
that first year. So, I was meant to fill
in for just 1 year until they found
someone else and that was somehow 19
years ago.
>> When you took over CS50, it feels like
the the course completely changed. When
you got into it, was your first thought
I want to take this online and kind of
make all these major changes or was that
a process over time?
>> Very much a process and so what people
see now is really a evolution of the
class as opposed to some overnight
revolution, so to speak. Um the online
aspect really started with Harvard
Extension School since I was fortunate,
right place right time, um to be
teaching that Extension School course my
senior year when distance education, so
to speak, was becoming a thing and my
mentor and boss, Henry Leitner at
Harvard, offered me the opportunity not
only to teach this class, but also to
put it online, I think in the year 2000,
give or take. The very first year I
taught it, spring of 1999, we were still
filming the class, but on VHS. Um and
fun fact, at the time it was the
course's teaching fellows, who were in
fact my friends, who were also
undergraduates at the time, who were
doing the filming and operating a tripod
with a camera and I swear to God we
still have footage, probably on some VHS
tape, of one of the cameras going
when one of my dear friends and teaching
fellows fell asleep during the middle of
class. Um so, we've aspired to higher
production value since, but it was
really
but it happened very organically. So,
once we started participating in the
Extension School's online education
program for several years, uh Apple
released the iPod around 2003 or 4, give
or take, and so at the time we were
distributing the course's videos via
RealVideo
and or RealAudio, which are older
technologies now, but were
state-of-the-art for streaming at the
time. We figured out a way how to sort
of download all of those bits for
redistribution as MP3s initially
and put them on iTunes, which back in
the day you could upload and maybe still
today your own RSS file, which is a
flavor of XML, which is kind of similar
to HTML, but more custom, that just
describes what and where your audio
files are. And we made this available
primarily for our own Harvard Extension
School students because at the time,
even though it was very progressive to
have streaming, it was a little annoying
that you needed a constant internet
connection. Buffering hadn't really been
invented yet. Certainly downloading
those videos was by design not possible.
But with podcasting, of course, you
could download the assets in advance.
And for our own students, the vision was
that they could listen to the class only
on audio at the gym or during their
commute. And just generally make the
educational content a little more
accessible. A year or two later, Apple
released the video iPod. And so we very
much steered into that and downloaded
those same assets, but in video form, to
make them available on the video iPod
and people's Macs and later PCs.
And we were fortunate around that time
early 2000s where Wired Magazine took
notice and um
noted for us that we were among the most
popular podcasts in some category. And
it was kind of news to us that people
cared. We we did know that we were
starting to see bandwidth problems at
the very early day in the very early
days we were using DreamHost to host the
MP3 files. And DreamHost had, I think,
free accounts, but only up to some
number of megabytes per month. And we
kept hitting the threshold. And so what
we would do is sign up for another
DreamHost account, another DreamHost
account, another DreamHost account. And
we would use like DNS trickery to just
reroute the
the URLs in the RSS file to the new web
host to keep up. Um so that's when all
of our attention is sort of was drawn to
the possibilities and that we can make
available this content not just for our
own students, but for anyone else who
either geographically, socioeconomically
couldn't access
uh that same kind of class. I
>> I see. So, the idea was it was a
supplementary
material for people who had paid for the
Harvard Extension School. And then,
[clears throat] but other people just
open on the internet could listen if
they wanted.
>> Yeah, and that that alone was a touchy
subject on campus at first because here
we were giving away the very thing that
other people were paying for. But, at
the end of the day, what people are
paying for is the additional support
structure you get in a more traditional
environment, the more traditional
credentialing, the transcript and the
credit, and so forth. But, the knowledge
itself, um it does society no good to
withhold that, I think.
>> [sighs]
>> So, I think this is a brutal reality of
making content on the internet. There's
so much competition for attention that
all the content has to kind of hook
people. Let's say you're scrolling on on
Instagram, that first second's really
got to capture someone, otherwise you're
going to go to the next one.
And I'm curious because you are making
content for the internet with these
lectures that you post online. Do you
think about how can I, you know, hook
the audience? Does that ever factor into
your your lecture design?
>> Lectures, no.
Um some of our social content, yes,
insofar as we are producing in addition
to the course's traditional in-classroom
content,
um things that are designed clearly for
social media, whether it's interviews,
for instance, whether it is excerpts
from CS50's Fair, this exhibition of
final projects, whether it's steering in
the directions of some popular meme just
to sort of catch the attention of our
own students or new students.
But, we have been very deliberate over
the years from the beginning and
especially since the age of the MOOC in
2012 when Coursera and edX and other
platforms were coming around to not
steer into this bite-sized, 3-minutes,
5-minutes chunks um that
I know there is data to confirm that it
drives engagement, but not necessarily
educational outcomes.
Um we have fairly unusually in recent
years stuck to the more traditional
model of like CS50's lectures are like 3
hours long and there are downsides to
that absolutely, but ironically online
you avoid some of the in-person
downsides because you can pause and
rewind and fast-forward, you can search
for something, open another tab, go down
this intellectual rabbit hole or rewind
to figure out what it what some detail
you missed. I mean, I I can't even count
how many times in college, high school,
school more generally that I'm sure I
zoned out and it's too often the case
that if you miss some detail, you're now
you might as well leave the class at
that point. And like online
solves that for you and I haven't seen a
need pedagogically for us to break up
the content into such small pieces and
to sort of take that ownership away from
the students. Um I think we'd prefer
that they meet us halfway and if you
need to take more than 3 hours to watch
a lecture, that's totally fine, but it's
not designed for scrolling type
consumption, I would say.
>> Right. What about in the in the idea of
like a long video? There's still this
concept that you kind of want to keep
people engaged and so how do you keep
people engaged for a 3-hour lecture?
>> Yes, so that we are very conscious of
and the way we've generally described
that is trying to create memorable
moments and this is not for social
media, this is as much for the in-person
audience as it is for the online
audience and by memorable moments I mean
in like CS50's first lecture, we do this
bit where I'll tear a phone book in half
um to demonstrate the the performance of
something called binary search, an
algorithm for finding information more
quickly than linearly searching the
phone book one page at a time. And
that's really just to be dramatic. Um it
has less and less impact these days
because most students uh if school age
are no longer familiar with the
technology known as a phone book, but
it's literally analogous to the digital
form in iOS or in Android, of course,
and so it doesn't take a huge leap for
someone to realize, "Okay, this is the
physical incarnation of that." And it's
just kind of fun, even though it's
getting harder and harder to find the
actual phone books. Um when we get to
searching algorithms and sorting
algorithms, we very often have a student
come up on stage, for instance. And for
sorting or for searching, we have a
whole bunch of like gym lockers, small
versions thereof, that we put numbers
in, either on printed paper or little
plastic numbers. And the goal is to have
a student like find the number 50 or
some other number that we've hidden
behind the doors. And it's an
opportunity just to talk about either
searching the doors linearly, left to
right, right to left, maybe you randomly
maybe more methodically as by a binary
search if the numbers are sorted. That
then leads us to opportunities to talk
about bubble sort and selection sort and
insertion sort. Algorithms that you
probably wouldn't bother implementing or
using in the wild cuz there's more
performant ones, certainly. But we use
them as these pedagogical tools to
explore the the problem to be solved,
which is, all right, I can only use
binary search if the data is sorted. So,
how do I sort it? And how expensive is
that going to be to make worthwhile the
whole process in the get-go? And so,
we'll have uh eight students come up on
stage and sort themselves physically and
really perform in certain ways. And
there's so many examples of that through
CS 50. We try to do at least one such
thing every class. I mean, not unlike
the way John Oliver, for instance, ends
Last Week Tonight. We're trying to do
some big song and dance, which
ironically is always at the end as the
hook. We do try to put it maybe toward
the beginning of lecture or in the
middle. But that's not just for
engagement and not to
make to keep folks' attention, but
really to latch onto their memories. So,
that even if you're in the weeds of this
introductory computer science course,
there's so much new information, it's
the proverbial fire hose hitting you in
the face,
you can cling to, okay, all right, I
remember like my my roommate was
literally the one on stage acting out
bubble sort. And you can kind of picture
in your mind's eye what was happening.
Or that phone book example is a perfect
one that years after leaving Harvard, we
have alumni coming up to us and saying,
oh, I still remember the phone book
demo. And those memorable moments,
ideally theatrical in nature, I think
are what brings material, whether it's
CS or something else, to life. But that
is very much to engage any learner,
present or remote, um as opposed to
being optimized for some technology.
>> One thing that I I wonder cuz computer
science is such a dense topic where I
guess there could be a trade-off with
Yeah, imagine another style of lecture
is uh you know, there's a chalkboard and
you're up there kind of blandly writing
out all of the information. I I could
imagine you could go through much more
depth in that case. Do you feel like
there's any trade-off there?
>> Absolutely. I mean, this is a criticism
we get from some students, particularly
those with prior background or among
those more comfortable, where do we
really need 10 minutes on linear search
or, you know, another 15 minutes on
binary search? And the answer is quite
clearly no for those students. And even
for most students, I would say we do
spend a disproportionate amount of time
on certain cherry-picked topics that we
do think lend themselves to this
theatricality
for really getting students interested
in fundamentally and excited by the
material to help motivate them the rest
of the week when they're going to be
spending 5, 10, 15, 20 plus hours on
some week's assignment and to help them
see sort of the forest for the trees.
Like, what is actually important and
meaningful and fun about this? Because
it's probably not the keystrokes and the
debugging and the lower-level
implementation details. So, we talk
about this actually in a paper in a talk
we we gave at a CS education conference
a few years back trying to find that
balance between the theatricality and
the density of material. But to your
question about dryness, I mean, I would
like to think that dryness really has no
place in most forms of education
because, you know, then it could have
been a book or it could have been an
email. Like, if it's just someone
reciting words or worse, writing things
down in ways that aren't at all
interactive. Like, do we really need to
be all in this room together? Like, that
doesn't seem like the best design to me.
>> In my research and looking at the
reception of CS50 and people's
perspective on how you are as an
educator, they absolutely love your
energy and like your delivery.
Do you rehearse that or is that
something that you always had as an
educator?
>> Yeah, I think it's just the sort of
expression. You got to bring your A-game
when you get up onto stage. And I think
a lot of it honestly comes from a place
of insecurity. Like, I really don't want
to be the one on stage in front of a
bored audience. Like, no one wants to be
in that situation. And so I think a lot
of the energy that I try to bring to
bear and the excitement I show is really
meant to one, make sure people want to
be and stay there for the duration of
the class, whether it's short or long,
and also help them see
the excitement in and the possibilities
of and the applicability of a field that
I myself had fell in love with so many
years ago.
Um, because then they can decide for
themselves if they feel that same
emotion, if they too look forward to
going home to their dorm or their home
on Friday nights and working on
programming assignments of all things.
But, I feel like we certainly owe them,
and I think teachers owe students more
generally educationally, the opportunity
to make that decision for themselves and
to
put uh forward our best foot or to
present the field in the most
exciting and inspiring way that we can,
if indeed we think it's important that
other people after us study and research
and apply these fields.
>> I noticed this uh dichotomy in education
when I was going to UCLA, which was
there were roughly two types of
professors that I had. There was one
type of professor that was beloved by
the students and really passionate at
educating and kind of involved. And then
there's this other type of professor,
which was really they might have been
really incredible and impressive as
researchers,
but their classes were really
uh poorly rated by all the students. And
with the online education that we can do
today, I mean like CS50, all the
resources are available. I could imagine
that objectively we could take the
people who are most passionate about
teaching and give it to everyone rather
than having some teachers that are not
excited. Kind of consolidate Take
Imagine taking the world's best
instructor and giving that to everyone.
Why doesn't consolidation happen if we
have all the technology for spreading
literally the world's best resources to
every situation?
>> Yeah, that's a good question since I
think our own goal is certainly not to
put out of business other educators,
other classes. However, as a computer
scientist, I would be among the first to
notice that there's a huge inefficiency
in the way education broadly works, not
only in this country, but presumably um
internationally as well, whereby you
have hundreds, thousands of teachers
essentially all doing the same thing in
parallel and not necessarily the
meaningful part of interacting with and
uplifting and mentoring students, but
like preparing their their presentations
or their lecture notes or writing the
assignments or grading that work.
There's so much meta work involved in
education that probably doesn't need to
be borne by so many people that the
computer scientist in me like invariably
wants to factor that out somehow. And so
I absolutely think that we educationally
as universities, as schools should be
leaning on each other much more. Um I'd
like to think that's a lot of what
drives us in terms of CS50's own mission
and the work that we do, but we too have
encountered frictions along the way. Um
it was very unusual for instance for 10
years that we were collaborating with
our friends down the road in New Haven
at Yale University where we were
offering CS50
on both campuses in parallel. And more
recently we've been doing this um with
some of our friends at Oxford in the
lifelong learning group there. This is
very much still the exception to the
rule. Unfortunately, even after
10 plus years of MOOCs, massive open
online courses,
I dare say a lot of institutions, a lot
of faculty are very set in their ways.
In fact, one of my regrets of the COVID
era were that we was that we had this
unpresed opportunity now and almost
mandate to move everything online and we
therefore had this opportunity to say,
"Hey, to Harvard students, why don't you
take this Stanford course or this UCLA
course or this Yale course or this MIT
course that you couldn't necessarily
take in person
uh for lack of transport or for lack of
safety at the time. And I could get no
one on campus to to get on board with
this idea of maybe offering one computer
science course on this campus and let
the other students take it. Then you
offer, as we did it yeah, like a digital
humanities class on some other campus
and let the Harvard students take it.
And there's just not much of an
appetite, I dare say in higher education
if not education at large, for that
resource sharing. And I think there
should be. Um I don't think there should
be one computer science course,
introductory course. I think some
healthy competition is a good thing. I
don't think there need to be thousands,
probably not hundreds, maybe dozens from
some of the best teachers, the best
schools um would probably benefit us all
if those same teachers then were not put
out of work, but then could lean on each
other, use some of the materials we've
created, adopt or as we say adapt some
of our own resources and treat education
as a buffet of educational materials
that you can then make your own without
having to do so much of the same legwork
and reinventing wheels across
school and state lines.
>> The mindset that you said, the the
computer scientist mindset of getting
rid of the redundancies and kind of um
consolidating resources, I mean, it's
immediately logically obvious to me, but
um what would like let's say there's
there's three top courses in America.
There's like MIT's, there's
Stanford's, and there's Harvard's, and
you know, they want to give that to
other institutions like I don't know,
other other colleges.
What would What would stop those
colleges from taking an objectively
better set of resources and giving that
to their students?
>> I sense, but I would defer to others who
who hold these views that there is a
concern that maybe we are putting
ourselves out of business or there's
more of a a school pride and Did I
definitely saw some of that on Harvard's
own campus where like, "No, no, no, no.
We like we should be offering courses to
our students that we have created and
that we are teaching and not lean for
instance on our friends down the road at
MIT who have and have for decades had a
larger, richer course catalog than us
simply by nature of being a bigger place
at least for computer science and it
seems silly to me not to lean on each
other. Maybe each of us can specialize a
bit more. Maybe each of us can offer
slightly different modes of of
instruction for students. Maybe that's a
little more intimate on this campus
versus that so as to really leverage
shared resources. I mean, this is done
endlessly in research having
cross-campus collaborations.
And there's something very personal
about or very
fundamentally threatening, I think,
about leaning on each other
educationally and I wish people would
move away from this mindset because it
doesn't mean some failure of the
institution to offer these courses. It
means we can do a better job offering
what resources we do have, I would like
to think.
>> In designing the curriculum for CS50,
how did you pick C for instance? Because
I think a lot of people would look at
that decision and think
I'm not going to use C in my day-to-day
full stack job. So, why do I need to
learn this?
>> Sure. Um so, it was not picked by me per
se, but I chose to keep C in the course
certainly since as far back as 1996 when
Brian was teaching it, Professor Margo
Seltzer before that, and many other
faculty prior to me and them. Um
it is
a wonderful foundation on which to build
your understanding of how a computer
works and how software is built. It's
about as close as you can get to the
hardware before things devolve, at least
aesthetically, into assembly code, which
is much scarier looking code, I think,
for most people, almost everyone,
perhaps. Um and certainly uh beyond that
is zeros and ones, which is not going to
be fun for anyone. Um so C kind of
strikes, I think, pedagogically this
really nice balance of having
English-like syntax and abstractions on
top of lower-level primitives that allow
you to explore procedural programming,
uh in particular, with some fundament
constructs that are now fundamental to
those kinds of languages, loops and
conditions and functions and variables
and return values and so forth. It sort
of got It's got everything, but it's
also a pretty small language, and unless
you download third-party stuff, there's
not a very large standard library, in
fact. So most anything you want, you
need to build yourself. And so we
leverage this significantly in CS50, so
much so that by mid-semester in week
five of the class, students are building
their own hash tables, and we're talking
about how you could construct singly
linked, doubly linked lists, uh
hash tables and tries, uh trees, yeah,
abstract data types like stacks and
queues and so many more. And what I
think is especially meaningful about C
is that you can't just instantiate one
of those data structures if you want
one, like you can in Java and C++ with
STL and certain other libraries. Like,
if you want it, you're going to have to
build it yourself. And I think that
alone is a good educational exercise,
not because you're going to need to
build that thing again, but because
there's value, I think, in really
understanding from the bottom up what is
going on inside of that device, so that
one, you can make more informed
decisions as to how you want to engineer
and design your own data structures down
the line. Two, you can
diagnose problems by reasoning through
first principles What could possibly go
wrong because you understand how the
data is being stored and what the
algorithms are that are performing on
that data. Um and three, it's a
wonderful scaffold to higher-level
languages because one of my favorite
things from week five to six in CS50 is
students go from having written the week
in week five like their own hash tables
implementation
uh for adding data, retrieving data, and
so forth, which is like this many lines
of code for some font size. And it it
gets whittled down in week six to one
line where you just instantiate a Python
dictionary. But and you can be
productive with a dictionary and many
courses do teach programming by way of
Python alone and we too have done it for
some of our audiences.
But you really never get around to
understanding what's going on underneath
the hood. And our goal in CS50 among
them is not to uh output programmers,
but engineers and educated citizens and
folks who really understand from first
principles how technology works. And so
C for instance strikes I think just that
right balance. And for those students
who want to go even deeper in a systems
class, they can go learn about assembly
and compilers and so forth. Um but those
students who want to go on to web
programming or data science stuff or AI
nowadays can just build on top of the C
and then in turn Python um layers that
we use in the class.
For this podcast, I produced transcripts
for every episode for convenient
skimming and I built a custom tool to
automate that.
Recently, I noticed in the Barbara
Liskov transcript my simple
speech-to-text tool was getting a lot of
things wrong. For instance, the CLU
programming language is spelled all caps
CLU, not CLU.
So, to fix this, I used Cursor 3, picked
the strongest version of Opus 4.7 extra
high, and had an agent make a plan to
fix that. And while I was waiting, I
figured I'd trigger a few more agents
for code cleanups and front-end
improvements.
Um it generated a reasonable plan with
rich system diagrams. It applied all the
changes within minutes and worked on the
first try.
So, if you want to build something with
the flexibility of sending off a bunch
of agents with frontier models of your
choice, you can go to cursor.com to try
out Cursor 3.
>> This is not my [snorts] perspective, but
um I was doing research and I saw a
YouTube video that said, "Whatever you
do, don't take CS50." Clickbait,
whatever. Yeah, I So, I watched the
video and the person worked. Yeah, it
got me. It got me. And the perspective
of the author of this video was that
CS50 teaches you all this stuff that you
don't really need to know if you were
like a full stack engineer or something.
Like, if you if I was just going into
the industry and I'm just making web
apps, that a lot of this um underlying
stuff you you might not need. And so,
maybe it's not a good use of time. And
I'm curious what you would say to
someone that has that that mindset that
you don't need to actually know how the
computer works.
>> I don't want to get into a whole
internet fight here, but I think that is
absolutely the wrong mindset. Certainly
for a full stack engineer. I mean, by
definition of full stack, you should be
understanding everything that's
happening among those layers. So, I
think the better formulation isn't that
you don't need to know these things, but
rather you won't need to use these
things. Use in a literal sense. Like, I
don't my C is a very popular language
even according to some rankings each
year. It's, you know, the number one,
number two language in terms of its
omnipresence still to this day because
it's very highly performant. Um
albeit more challenging to write than
some languages. I only use C for 5 weeks
during CS50 itself, but that doesn't
mean that it hasn't helped me understand
higher-level languages, what is going on
inside of a system, how you can improve
the performance of or the design of some
system by understanding again those
first principles.
Uh I don't use Scratch except for 1 week
out of the year. I do use Python more
frequently and I use JavaScript and some
HTML and CSS, but I think if you're
going to call yourself an engineer, you
should absolutely
have mastery of and knowledge of those
underlying building blocks if you want
to not just output something that
frankly AI could output nowadays, but
you can understand and you can create
the next thing or the solution to some
other problem that we haven't even yet
solved. Um I think that's the better
mindset to appreciate yes, I'm not going
to need to use Scratch or C or maybe
some of the other things we touch on in
CS50, but the knowledge and the
principles that we extract from those
implementation details are incredibly
valuable. If you want to be an engineer
and not just say
a coder, is which is a distinction that
some folks might make.
>> I was looking at the syllabus and
there's C obviously and there's all the
I mean, you know, basic data structures,
those types of things, bread and butter.
And then in the end of the course,
there's the a week on artificial
intelligence, which I was surprised to
see in a intro course because it's kind
of like
there's no way that you could teach
AI in a week. So I I'm assuming it's a
more high-level introduction.
>> It is. It's only for an hour and it
technically temporally it's offered in
the middle of the semester for the
on-campus students. Um it coincides by
design with uh family weekend when uh
first years and juniors uh students'
parents come to town very frequently. Um
and so we do it as a very broad
introduction to what everyone is talking
about
nowadays in the AI space. Um there are
full-fledged classes of course at
Harvard and other institutions that
students can take and it's really meant
to wet their appetite, but also give
them some context for the very tools
we're using in CS50. We have this
virtual rubber duck that's built on top
of OpenAI's APIs and Microsoft Azure's
web ser- API service um that they're
using every day or every week certainly
throughout CS50. So among the goals
pedagogically is to help them understand
what are the tool how do the tools work
that you yourself have been using.
Two, to help them understand what is it
that the world is talking about
nowadays, and three, is prepare them to
use these tools more effectively by the
end of the semester because for instance
for CS50's final project, students are
encouraged and welcome to use Claude or
ChatGPT or Gemini or any number of
off-the-shelf AI tools that we don't
allow those through policy for the
course's assignments.
>> Yeah, I had a conversation with a
another professor and a specifically
about um you know, is AI affecting how
the kids are learning?
And uh his perspective was it was kind
of um maybe he didn't do it properly and
the students were over-relying on it and
I think that is a concern that a lot of
people have is that students these days
can be more brain-dead. Like you could
just go to ChatGPT and say, "Honestly,
just solve the problem for me."
For you as an educator in computer
science, what is the ideal uh
relationship with AI for your students?
>> Yeah, so this virtual rubber duck at
cs50.ai, which anyone with a free GitHub
account can use, um is really meant by
design to be a less helpful version of
ChatGPT, one that is also more tuned to
CS50's own material and syllabus and so
forth. Um and that's because all of
these tools off-the-shelf can pretty
much do your homework for you. And this
has been true for several years even
before the fall of 2022 when ChatGPT
came out. I mean, we were looking
closely at GitHub Copilot for some time
because if you created an empty text
file in VS Code called mario.c, which is
the file name we use for one of CS50's
pro
problem sets, and if you so much as
type, I think, hash and then I for
include, you pretty much get a
suggestion to auto-complete the entirety
of that particular problem set. Um and
that's just because I mean, we for
better for worse are part of these
models in so far as the open courseware
has presumably been slurped up as with
the rest of the internet as part of the
training data, so to speak, for these AI
models. Um so, that has both good and
bad, and that's why we set out to make
our own sort of duck-themed version of
these tools that puts downward pressure
on that willingness of the tools to be
too helpful, and we've tried to attune
the duck to be more akin to a good
teacher or tutor that leads you to the
solution, but certainly doesn't
auto-complete your whole way through it.
>> I see. So, there's uh like a system
prompt, there's some scaffolding that
says,
"Don't answer the question, but help me
figure it out."
>> Pretty much. And it's much easier to do
this now than it was in 2022 and 2023
when we first rolled this out, um which
is to say, there's a lot of tools, even
commercial tools, that faculty can use
to do the same kind of thing for their
own course. Um for us, it was important
to draw a clean line in the sand to
students because you could approximate
this duck by just telling students, "Hey
everyone, go copy-paste this system
prompt, as you described, into ChatGPT
before you ask your homework question."
And no one's going to do that, and like
that's going to drift out of date, and
it just feels too clunky. Students are
just going to end up typing into the
prompt. Whereas, I think it's a lot
cleaner, um if not simpler, to know I
cannot, through policy,
go to ChatGPT, Gemini, Copilot, any of
these things, but I can go to and use as
much as I want cs50.ai or the plugin we
have in VS Code of the same. Um and that
to me is a very healthy line because you
know if you're crossing that line, if
you're pulling up chat.openai.com or
gemini.google.com and the like, um and
that at that point it's a conscious
choice to be academically dishonest, as
we would describe it in CS50's syllabus.
>> When I was going through my CS
education, um
cheating was already pretty rampant. Um
I mean, people put their code on GitHub,
and you kind of paraphrase someone
else's code. Well, not me, but other
people. Okay.
>> [laughter]
>> And uh I I imagine with the new
technology that actually, I mean, with
with anything with cheating, it's
adversarial. There's people who are
cheating, and there's people who trying
to catch the cheaters, right?
I could imagine that the cheating tools
are advancing faster than the ability to
catch them because you just generate the
code, it's not easy to say, "Oh, that
was um you know, AI generated or
whatever."
So, uh I'm curious if you see more
cheating on your end and um yeah,
generally if you're catching more of
dishonesty.
>> Statistically Statistically we are not
catching more. I would like to think
that the
behave the misbehavior has not markedly
increased if only because we, like a lot
of intro courses around the world,
um have a tradition of looking for
academic dishonesty, plagiarism, code
that was copied and pasted off the
internet or YouTube video. And we,
within CS50, like a lot of peer
institutions, are very good at catching
that. Like we have tools that
cross-compare all of student submissions
against each other, against GitHub
repositories of past submissions that we
have, of YouTube videos that have been
transcribed. So, we have historically
administratively disciplined, so to
speak, between 5 and 10% of CS50 student
body every semester. And that's kind of
a norm among across peer institutions,
you know,
upper bound of roughly 10%. There's
certainly probably some percentage of
students who have been cheating in some
form all these years and never have been
detected.
But just based on the rigor with which
we go through this, the messaging
throughout the course, and like I like
to think that a good 90% of students are
behaving in the way that they should, at
least when the boundaries are set
through not only policy, but course
culture, and through the support
structure that we provide to students.
Um
That said, um we've not seen an uptick
in uh in what in detections of academic
dishonesty. Um I a uh what has gotten
harder is the so-called prosecution of
those cases in the sense that it's
harder for us now to hand to the
administrative board of Harvard or the
honor council, so to speak, a smoking
gun. Like, here is the URL from which
this code was copied because it's not
really coming from a URL or a YouTube
video, it's coming from the composition
of all of the URLs out there and all of
the YouTube videos about CS50's problem
sets because the AI somewhat
pseudo-randomly is spinning out an
amalgam of these various training
inputs. Um that said, when you've been
doing this long enough, like you can
tell that this is not the work of this
particular student, either in comparison
to past work that they submitted or the
sophistication with which they're
solving a problem or the incorrectness
with which they're solving the problem
and there's often telltale signs like
this is not this year's problem set,
this is last year's and so clearly this
did not come from you alone. So, we
certainly are able to detect the easier
to detect behaviors.
>> Right. 5 to 10%
that feels
uh spiritually like a lot. Like, one out
of 10 students uh doing something, but I
mean, you have the
>> Yeah, I mean, 20 years ago I probably
would have agreed after seeing it year
after year after year, I'm just glad
it's not higher than that.
>> On the topic of uh AI, a lot of students
they see where these uh
these agentic tools are going. They're
generating code that is superhuman in
many cases and I think it gives people
the sense of dread. Like, imagine you're
spending all this time
getting better at programming and you
think that maybe programming will be
useless in the future.
You know, if a anxious student comes to
you and says, "I don't know if I should
be learning computer science." What
would you say?
>> I wouldn't worry about getting better at
programming. The whole point of so many
of these courses has been about getting
better at problem solving and like that
is a life skill, whether you're going to
stay in CS or tech uh more generally or
leave it for some other fields in which
there's still going to be problems, just
different types of problems. And there
too is why we constantly tell students
the course is not about Scratch and C
and Python and JavaScript. Like these
are all implementation details, and
while they definitely have and
consciously have pedagogical value,
that's why they're in the syllabus. The
goal is not to teach students Scratch
and C and Python and JavaScript, but how
to solve problems and to give them
representative tools with which they can
solve those problems and also an
understanding of those same first
principles from which they can reason
about some symptom they're seeing or
some problem they are ultimately trying
to solve. Um AI is pretty darn good
already at generating code. It's only
going to get better, but that's
wonderful far as it's going to save us
humans from the stuff that was never
very fun to begin with. Even I am guilty
of never really writing as many like
unit tests for my code to test the
correctness automatically. That stuff
can be very easily and robustly
generated nowadays. What I don't want
the computer to take from me is sort of
the fun part of that it the the fun part
that's always been there, which is the
designing of the system itself. Maybe
thinking about what the UX should be so
that you can optimize for the user
experience or what the database design
might be or what data you want to
collect in pursuit of some business
problem because you know you're going to
need to analyze or mine it for some
valuable insight later on. Like that
stuff's probably not going away anytime
soon. And the other reassurance I would
give students nowadays is like the world
is only getting more technological.
And we've kind of seen this pattern
before where I took CS50 for instance at
really the peak of the so-called dot-com
era. So 1996 and then sort of the world
started trending down when all the
startups were going out of business and
students were exiting computer science.
But like then the pendulum swung back
and I don't think we have saturated the
world in terms of technology. Every
business small and large is probably
going to keep using it more and more. We
in our personal lives are only going to
keep needing it more and more. And so
like those are problems to be solved.
And yes, I don't think we'll need as
many humans to write HTML and CSS
anymore, which was at the risk of
picking another fight, never that much
fun anyway.
And maybe we won't really need to use C
or Python anymore, but we can start
programming like a PM, a product
manager, using our voice, using our
words in English or some other human
language, but that all that alone would
be wonderful. Um case in point, I was
playing with Claude this morning to just
help me prototype something, and it was
wonderful for me to be able to just
think about the problem and sort of the
engineering side of it and say, all
right, Claude, much like an intern,
please go implement this for me because
I really don't want to go reading the
documentation, which was never that
intellectually interesting. I could if I
wanted to, and I understand how it's
structured, but I don't need to keep
repeating that kind of exercise again
and again. But at least in the near
term, case in point, Claude came back
very confidently with a solution that
was like 90% correct, and I had to
convince Claude, so to speak, by
chatting back with it that like no, no,
no, no, like this is not possible per
the API docs at this URL. So, of course,
you get the apologetic response from the
LLM, and this kind of error rate or
hallucination will decrease with
frequency, but like this is why the
human should stay in charge for some
time.
>> In in today's environment, it we can
relatively confidently say these tools
empower us and they don't replace fully
yet. But I think a lot of people are
worried about, okay, but what if, you
know, it gets What if it gets even
better? Like what if that 90% becomes
99% or, you know, maybe it becomes 100%?
Then I think people get scared, but you
know, it's hard to say exactly in the
future.
>> But in so far as our goal within even a
class like CS50 has always been to out
to output a more educated citizenry, to
teach students how to teach themselves,
to
teach them how to be more methodical,
more algorithmic in problem solving,
like all of that is valuable whether or
not we have robots doing work for us in
our future, I think.
>> You talked about the enrollment rates,
and I have this uh little screenshot cuz
you had written this I think this paper
from long time ago about redesigning
CS50, and you kind of I'll put this
overlay this in the video, but um you
know, there's this trend of kind of
enrollment rates going up, and then they
they tank with the top dot-com bubble,
and then they went up as well because of
some adjustments that you made. And then
right now we're kind of in this um you
know, AI is really shifting things. How
if you were to continue this graph
forward, is enrollment and interest in
computer science declining because of
the uh AI?
>> Oh, lately, that absolutely seems to be
the case. And that was preceded, I
think, over the past few years really by
the downturn in tech offerings. Uh I
mean, we were seeing this in the
recruiting pipeline on campus where
there were just fewer opportunities, and
there was less of an appetite among some
of the big tech companies to even bother
coming to campus if they just didn't
have many entry-level roles for
students, and that was before ChatGPT
and similar tooling was sort of
omnipresent. So, AI has only
exacerbated, I think, that concern. Um
but I think what we're going to see if
we sort of extrapolate out is that
there's going to be these ebbs and flows
over the years, um much like we've seen
or the pendulum swinging each uh
different way, whatever whichever
metaphor you prefer. Um just as humans
have a tendency, I do think, especially
in tech to overreact to things both
positively and negatively. And while AI
is absolutely here to stay, I do think
it's going to become equivalent in our
minds to just what technology is. AI is
a nice sort of buzzword and way to
distinguish it from some of the more
deterministic or um
predictable outcomes that like
technology to date has maybe had. But
you know, I think back even over my 19
years with CS50, and you know, AR and VR
was to be all the rage, and then and had
blockchain and Bitcoin, and uh Google
Glass even like excited the imagination
like no other technology at the time.
And all of these things are still with
us in some form or some future
incarnation. And especially with
blockchain and Bitcoin, like there's
some resiliency there. And AR and VR are
still very omnipresent in games, but
it's just been fascinating to watch the
world, the tech world, especially the VC
world, sort of react and overreact
habitually to these kinds of things
until we sort of find a healthier medium
where people appreciate the the real
value and not just the opportunistic
value of it all.
>> You're in a unique position because you
you teach the in-person Harvard class,
and then you also do the massively
online version as well. And I think it's
an interesting case study because
um
some people have the opinion that the
important part of college is actually
not the education.
And it feels like this this
um you know, in-person version versus
the online one is is kind of proof of
that, which is that
you could not go to Harvard, but get a
world-class education, yet the outcomes
are very different. So, I'm curious your
your thoughts on
uh going to college versus getting the
world-class education for free.
>> Yeah, I think it depends on your goals.
I think there's absolutely value of
places like Harvard really because of
that credentialing. And also, it's a
filter from the get-go. I mean, these
admissions departments are already
identifying strengths among people and
sort of the audience you then end up
with is very similar along certain axes,
certainly along academic abilities and
whatnot. But the value of places like
Harvard I do think has long been the
networking opportunities, the
connections you make, the life
experiences you might have. And
academics sometimes to a fault, like is
uh is often secondary. But when it comes
to knowledge and learning outcomes and
practical skills, I mean, I'd like to
think that you're getting as good if not
better an experience taking a class like
CS50 online if only for the simple
technological reasons that you can pause
and fast forward and rewind and open
multiple tabs, go down this intellectual
rabbit holes in ways that a traditional
campus is just not designed to support
unless those same students are taking
the class in their dorm rooms or at home
like like during COVID.
>> You've taught so many years of this same
material. What is the the most
difficult concept that you see people
consistently having trouble?
>> Pointers in C, and that was true for me
30 years ago. So much so that
I'm always very weirdly excited to tell
students in class nowadays that I still
remember where I was on campus the day I
finally got pointers and I'll share
here. I was in one of the dining halls
on campus with my teaching fellow or TF
who himself was a a student probably one
or two
one or two years older than me. We were
sitting at the back of the dining hall
on these wooden tables in this beautiful
old-school sort of Harvard-esque room
and somehow or other something he said
that day after weeks of struggling that
light bulb went off for me and I'm like,
"Oh, it's just an address." Which, you
know, never quite clicked even though
I'm sure many people tried to hammer
that into me previous to that, but it's
just hard. Like memory stuff is hard
especially if computers to students from
the get-go is very much this black box,
this abstraction itself, um to really go
down to that level takes some
some new thinking and it took me a
while.
>> Let's say someone is trying to help
someone else grasp a difficult concept.
Like what's your your best tip on how to
really teach someone something that
they're really struggling with?
>> I may my instinct is to say metaphors
and or what we more broadly call
memorable moments where it's a phone
book where you're trying to teach binary
search or even a screenshot of the iOS
contacts app where you're trying to uh
introduce the same algorithm. It's
during COVID for instance, we worked
with a local theater and we had seven
physical doors on a stage that were from
previous plays that they had put on and
we put fuzzy little numbers behind that
the prop shop had kindly developed for
us so that we could play that same game
of using not lockers but physical doors.
And creating those binary doors for
students, I think helps them latch onto
a visual that makes a very esoteric
topic that, frankly, who really cares
about binary search day to day, just
kind of come alive and you realize at
least back in the day of actual phone
books, like, "Oh, I've been using this
the whole time. I just didn't know what
to call it." And I think that's very
empowering to use metaphors to create
memorable moments that help students
realize that even the seemingly most
arcane topics are still very much within
their grasp and perhaps not so
dissimilar. Even when we talk about
binary for students, we like to show
them that, "Hey, here's a number like
123." Well, why is it 123? Cuz there's
the ones place, the tens place, the
hundreds place and so forth. Hey, guess
what? Binary is the exact same
methodology, but you just have the ones
place, the twos place, the fours place
and so forth. And helping people realize
like, "Oh, like that's all it is." I
think is very empowering cuz suddenly
they feel like they're part of the
conversation and they actually know what
they're talking about all the more even
when they thought that was a domain for
those more comfortable only.
>> OpenAI, Anthropic, Cursor, and Vercel
all use this product to make their lives
better.
And the problem it solves is when you're
building SaaS or an AI product and you
want to sell to other companies, there's
all these requirements you need to meet.
There's SSO, there's SCIM, there's RBAC,
there's audit logs. These are all things
that take time to integrate but aren't
the main focus of your app. WorkOS is an
API layer that lets you meet all of
these requirements in just a few lines
of code. So, let's say you have a new
SaaS product and you want to sell to
other companies, WorkOS will solve all
of these critical feature gaps for you.
You can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started. And I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast.
>> For people [snorts] who struggle, I
mean, this this idea of growth mindset
versus you're kind of born with some
innate talent and you've seen so many
students that I feel like you probably
have a perspective on this. But I I'm
curious if you think that there's anyone
that's just born that can't learn
computer science. And I that's not the
world that I want to live in, but you
know, let's just say you have someone
and you explain a race to them
you know, 100 times and they they kind
of don't get the concepts. Do you feel
like really you can kind of grow and and
learn?
>> I think to an extent. I mean, if you if
it's still not sinking in after 100
times, like I mean, frankly, I think
good educational advice would be like
maybe this isn't the field for you and
this is how you've been empirically
figuring that out. If it's just not
clicking in a way that's exciting you,
that's making you happy, then okay, stop
beating yourself up. Like find something
else that's of interest to you.
But if you're struggling and you're
thinking of giving up after two times,
10 times, 49 times, I'm not quite sure
where the cutoff is. Like you should
probably continue to try to power
through, not necessarily by taking that
same approach, but find some other
class, some other professor, some other
teaching assistant, some other book to
try a different perspective or angle on
it because maybe you're just not driving
with like the form of instruction or the
style of the teacher, myself included.
So I wouldn't give up thinking it's you
alone. Um and I do think too, that's
really the secret ingredient is time.
Like fine, if you don't if you can't
quite finish the course in 12 weeks,
take 24, take 52. Like that's perfectly
fine, especially if you're juggling
other things. This isn't necessarily
your primary focus. I think time is a
perfectly reasonable knob to turn and I
think that puts it well within reach of
so many other people.
>> CS50 is um beloved. People have The
reception online is so overwhelmingly
positive. And you've been doing it for
so long. What is next with CS50? Like do
you see yourself kind of continuing the
same curriculum for the next decade or
will things change?
>> Yeah, I think CS50 itself will continue
to evolve as it as it long has. I do
think it will continue to change both in
terms of tooling and concepts as AI sort
of permeates our lives and technology
all the more. That said, I think it's
always meant to be this introductory
course in problem solving. So, I think
there will be this backbone that remains
and has been there even since my day,
even though the problem sets are very
different nowadays, the style of the
lectures is very different. If you
really compare the syllabus from fall of
1996 versus now and uh what will be fall
2026, like they're not that
fundamentally different. They're just
packaged very differently and style-
ized, I think, very differently. But,
there's a lot of knowledge and
conceptual framework and practical
skills that are very invariant over the
years. Um what we have been doing in
recent years though is steering in the
direction of developing all the more of
a complete curriculum. So, courses that
students can take for free online
through OpenCourseWare after CS50, um
earlier courses, uh gentler courses that
students can take uh before CS50 itself
or even instead of CS50 itself,
depending on the goals that they have
and the background that they're
Um the plan in the near term is to
branch out beyond computer science,
working with a colleague of ours, Tom
Crawford, at the University of Oxford on
uh courses in maths or maths, as he
says, um in all sorts of fields so as to
help uplift students who are taking,
say, computer science courses, but don't
have the requisite math background that
might be ideal to have so that you don't
struggle with certain things that we
might otherwise just take for granted.
Um beyond that, uh STEM more broadly is
of interest, and while we're not expert
our experts ourselves, um working with
colleagues of ours in the arts and
humanities and trying to bring this form
of theatricality and these memorable
moments uh to a stage but with far more
people and subjects than me and mine.
>> When you mention math and these other
subjects, it kind of reminds me, I mean,
I haven't been in schooling system for a
long time, but uh Khan Academy was like
a very popular resource. I I imagine
that's still around and so that would be
I guess uh a competitor.
>> I do think some healthy competition is
good as if it drives different courses,
different teachers to sort of try new
things and teach differently. Um but I
think the more the merrier. The world
only benefits from more educational
resources. And so
>> if those are let's say I'm uh
Okay, let's say I'm a parent and I'm
deciding should I
put my high schooler in the Khan Academy
learning track of math or what you plan
to offer?
>> From what I've seen certainly of Khan
Academy's work is that their um like
ours I think is more of a cast of
characters, at least on video form. At
least I know the earliest of um Sal
Khan's work was sort of the handwritten
style for his niece or nephew, um which
was wonderfully compelling and engaging.
I think we stylistically are just very
different and I think we
try across CS50's courses traditionally
to have a a shared aesthetic, a shared
pedagogical style, a shared lecturing
style so that when you take uh a CS50
course, so to speak, you sort of know
what you're getting because it's very
similar in spirit to the others in the
ecosystem.
>> Coming to the end, like when you look
back on your your career, what is your
biggest regret?
>> I would say I wish someone had told me
or I wish I had known to just calm down.
Like at least when I was in university,
I was one of these students who again
came in thinking I was going to major in
something else, government in my case. I
was one of those students who went to my
first uh RA meeting, proctor meeting,
advisor meeting with probably on a sheet
of paper all 32 courses I thought I was
going to take at Harvard, which did not
come to pass, but it really led me
astray in some way the first year and a
half of school in that I was really
focused on crossing requirements off the
list, taking the courses I thought I
should, and it wasn't till sophomore
year that I took CS50, which was
eye-opening and allowed me to start to
pivot. But even then, I hadn't broken
out of that mold probably until senior
fall senior spring when I finally took
an introduction to Latin course, which
was just for fun and was just so
interesting and eye-opening and I
finally understood aspects of English
and Spanish retroactively that I never
really had mastered when taking those
same classes. I took a course on um
dramatic arts 101, which was a survey
class on theater and writing and set
design and and acting and pretty much
every elemental aspect of theater was
introduced in this class and I wish I
had thought to take a class like that.
And even in graduate school, I was only
gradually learning this lesson. Finally
audited essentially a a course in
archaeology, which was so much fun. So
much so I had this existential crisis
thinking maybe I should have gone to a
PhD in archaeology instead, but I I I
stayed with CS and I just wish someone
had told me to calm down early on and
sort of explore more, particularly areas
in which I thought I'd be less
comfortable. And that's at least a
message I try to give to students
nowadays.
As for professional regrets, thankfully
relatively few come to mind. If
anything, you know, I used to joke even
with some of our own TAs that in so far
as I've largely stayed in academia, you
know, I've never had a like a real job,
but um as recently as a recent
sabbatical, I spent a whole semester
essentially interning with GitHub as a
professor in residence and learning the
ropes of a real-world software
engineering company and having access to
the the internal issues and bug reports
and feature requests and sitting in as a
fly on the wall to some of the team
meetings and design chats. And it was so
much fun to actually live the life that
we've been teaching about for so long.
And there too, I wish I had done that
earlier or at least in parallel had done
maybe more consulting opportunities or
done a little bit more in the real world
before coming back to school and then
staying in school.
>> Did you ship a project or or like what
was that time at GitHub? Like what was
the
>> It wasn't I don't think I contributed
code. I definitely contributed issues
and bug reports and feature requests. My
sort of role was to be this educational
voice at the table, especially in the
design of certain products and to at
least speak up on behalf of educational
use cases, give teachers a voice at the
table when it came comes to certain
features that would really make the
student experience better, particularly
in tools like VS Code, albeit on the
Microsoft side or some of the internal
GitHub tooling. So, I don't think you'll
find any code that I wrote, but
hopefully one of my issues underlies
some code that's now in the code base.
>> What about looking back on your time
doing CS50? Like if you were to just
reflect on what went well and what
didn't go well, the just the highlights
of you know, your time running the
course, what what would you say?
>> I think it's been very meaningful, so
much so that it's become our mission
organically to have
this now tradition of open courseware
that wasn't certainly our own idea. It
was really inspired by our friends down
the road at MIT who really championed
this decades ago, but very happy with
how that has evolved because it's made
the work all the more meaningful in ways
that go beyond just education, but
helping as we've heard anecdotally from
some of our students out there very
professional impacts, life impacts,
being able to better care for your
family or to pivot professionally into a
field that you didn't think was for you.
Like that has just been very meaningful
and rather makes it all worthwhile. And
I hope too
in so far as we've been a bit unusual
both with our production volume and
openness trying to sort of offer an
example that others could follow that
hey maybe more people should be doing
this more people should be sharing
leaning on us us leaning on them because
I do think that's still a missed
opportunity educationally.
>> What's your best like technical book
recommendation if someone wants to learn
programming or if there's maybe some
other topic that you you know recommend
a book for you'd love to hear it.
>> My favorite book is Hitchhiker's Guide
to the Galaxy and I think everyone
should read that or play the terminal
based video game that existed when I was
growing up of it. Funny enough within
CS50's courses it's been a few years
since we officially recommended any
books. This is partly consistent with
our commitment to openness and for
everything being free so that there
isn't some financial barrier to someone
out there to needing a textbook for the
course. That said over the years and to
this day some of my favorite tech books
even though they're increasingly
outdated are this brilliantly colorful
picturesque easy to understand and
accessible
book called how computers work which we
used in that course I first taught in
1999 and how the internet works and I
think they eventually stopped updating
them some years ago but they were such
wonderful educational tools. I think
every subject should have a book that
looks quite like that. More arcanely
there's a book that we still recommend
to students unofficially or if they
really want to go pursue something more
arcane
in C called the Hacker's Delight which
is this wonderful hard cover book that
just has really neat neat bit trickery
and low level hacks low level techniques
you can use to make your C code
especially all the more performant so
there's a lot of value in a book like
that but I think back years ago to when
I was learning some stuff in technology
and like the For Dummies books was
great. I think for some time we might
have recommended one of the complete
idiots guides or something like that,
which doesn't have the best somatics,
but the reality is they are by design
written for a very broad, accessible
audience, and I think that has a lot of
value as opposed to the more traditional
textbook where you sort of have to have
taken the class in order to understand
the book.
>> Is there an official textbook for the
Harvard CS50, not the open one? Okay, so
that one also has the
>> Other than having access to a computer
and the internet, um there's no
financial requirements.
>> That's great. I I love that idea.
Last question for you is, you know, if
you could go back to the beginning of
your career and kind of give yourself
some advice, what would you say?
>> Explore more, I do think. I I wish I had
more jobs under my belt early on, which
I think was the result of my
being pulled back into choosing to go
back into academia. I think it would
have been healthy if I had allowed
myself maybe another year or two in
between undergrad and graduate school,
or it probably would have worked out
well if CS50 hadn't opened up for me
right as I was finishing my PhD, because
then I probably would have gone off to
industry for some amount of time.
That said, not sure I would have gotten
the job if I had wandered off campus at
that point, so it probably worked out
for the best, but I had such fun when I
was interning interning, so to speak, at
GitHub that it would be fun to live more
of the lives that some of my friends in
tech have lived.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
your time. I really appreciate it,
David.
>> Yeah, thanks so much.
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like.
Also, if you have any recommendations
for people you want me to bring on,
please drop a comment. Guests like
Barbara Liskov, Mike Stonebraker, Mark
Brucker, these were all people that I
brought on because someone left a
comment. On another note, aside from the
podcast, I'm working on building the
ergonomic keyboard that I wish existed.
Here's a glance at the prototype. It's a
split keyboard, so there's two sides.
Um this is in the case. But yeah, we
launched on Kickstarter and we hit our
goal within 8 hours of launching. I
really appreciate it if you were one of
the people who grabbed one of the early
units. Um we're now working on the long
journey of building the tooling now. And
so if you still want to pick one up,
I've left the late pledges open on
Kickstarter, so you can grab one there.
I'll put a link in the description.
Thank you again for watching the podcast
and